Hi, welcome back to the Wheel of Life
online retreat. We've reached session
number nine, and this is going to be a
meditation. And some of you have done
this meditation before during the Lion's
Dance meditation. But we're about to
discuss the Wheel of Life in detail.
We've been talking about how to go from
one life to another life, especially the
bardo (BAR DO). And now we're going to explore
that. By the way, I made a mistake in
the video yesterday, and I would like to
correct it. So there are two books about
how to help somebody in the bardo. And
the two names are very similar, and I
made a mistake yesterday. So the first
book is called bardo tu drul (BAR DO THOS GROL), which means "just
hearing about it you can be liberated in
the bardo." And that's the book which is
not considered authentic in our
Tsongkapa tradition,
and it has been translated in English as
the "Tibetan Book of the Dead" or names
like that. So I would encourage you to
rather use the great ancient books on
the Abhidharma, and that's the presentation I made
in this course. The book name I used
yesterday, which is bardo trang drul (BAR DO 'PHRANG SGROL)--
one word difference ... that means
"freedom from the narrow alleyway of the bardo." And
that's a great book. So I made a mistake
yesterday; I mentioned that book and that
that's a pretty famous jang chok (BYANG CHOG) or
"how to help somebody in the bardo." Also
yesterday, or a few days ago, we mentioned
the word bum ('BUM), like in Milarepa's "One Hundred
Songs." And the usual name of his book is...
the nickname is gur bum (MGUR 'BUM). gur
bum. So literally it means "one-hundred thousand
songs," but the "hundred thousand" just
means "a collection" of his songs; it's not
a hundred thousand.
There's a similar word sungbum (GSUNG 'BUM), which
means the collected works of any modern
Tibetan in the last one thousand years. So we
kind of... I think we translated it as "one hundred"
and not "one-hundred thousand," so it should be
translated as "one-hundred thousand." Okay, so we're going to
go through a meditation which is part of
the ancient Lion's Dance meditation, which
was taught by Buddha, and also Maitreya
and Asanga. And we're going to go on a
journey to our past life. But the purpose
of that is to explore dependence - or you
can call it dependent origination - which
is the meaning of the twelve links
inside the Wheel of Life. We're going to be
going deep into those twelve links
starting with the next session, session
ten. And there's a way that you can
explore them personally during a
meditation. So let's do that together. I'm going to put
on my meditation timer.
This is a nice timer. I would use it -
it's called Insight Timer. Okay, here we
go. Get comfortable on your seat. A little
bit of a smile. Of course there are serious
things happening in the world, but it
doesn't mean we have to go around with a
scowl on our mouths. These are the kind of times when
people need a smile, and they need us to
be friendly and warm towards them. Relax
your forehead. Relax your fingers. During
the meditation, try not to tighten your
forehead or get wrinkles on your forehead.
Personally, I find it very useful to
have a slight smile. The eyes are closed,
but they are focused a little bit up. And
it's very good to tighten the lower
abdomen, which strengthens the back. So
here we go.
We're going to start this meditation with
ten breaths. So let's count ten slow
breaths. By tradition, the out-breath...
the beginning of the breath is the
out-breath. And remember that I'm asking
you at the end of your out-breath to
push out a little more air. Let's enjoy ten
long exhale breaths. The inhale will take
care of itself.
And we'll do a quick seven-step
preliminary. So please invite one of your
teachers to come and sit in front of you.
Now let's make them a gift of
appreciation of some great quality of
theirs. Think of something about your
teacher that you really admire.
Now let's clean some bad seeds from
yesterday. Think of two or three mistakes
you made yesterday, and open up your
heart and admit them to your teacher.
Make a promise not to repeat them for
some length of time.
Now give equal time and energy to
thinking about a few good things you did
yesterday and telling your teacher.
Now as for teachings in your life, some
of them will come as positive
teachings and some of them will come as
challenges.
Now ask your teacher to please stay in
your life. You can see a big difference
between people who have a close
teacher and people who don't.
If we're lucky, we have a teacher we can
be close to.
Now let's go back to the beginning of
these preliminary steps. We are looking at
the teacher in front of us. Again, they
are alive and they are warm - they are a
real person. Now try to imagine something
about them that you really appreciate.
The reason they're your teacher is they
know something that you would like
to learn. They have certain habits or
certain skills that we would like to
learn. So think about just any one of
those. Why are you... why did you choose
them as a teacher? What do they have that
you don't have? What did they have that you
want to learn? Think about one thing - one
good quality.
Now think, "The reason I see this good
quality," if we go back to the the old
popular pen teaching ... "because a dog and a
human see a pen as a different thing
that shows that the pen is coming from
the human's mind and the same object is
being seen as a chew toy by the dog.
Therefore, the pen is not coming from the
pen. If the pen was coming from the
pen, then both the dog and the human would
see it as a pen. And the reason the human
sees a pen is that they have a seed in
their mind, and when they look at the
cylinder stick--the pen stick--when they
look on those parts, then the seed opens
in their mind
and an image made of light comes out of
the seed and it settles down on the pen--
on the cylinder--and that's why the human
sees a pen." Now, how that seed got into
the human's mind--karmic seed--we're going
to explore that during the Wheel of Life.
But we all know, "because of the first law
of karma--watermelons make watermelons--if
I see an instrument of communication
like a pen and that comes out of a
karmic seed in my mind, then I must have
helped some other people communicate in
the past. That also applies to the
beautiful quality I see in my teacher
right now. It's coming from a seed in my
mind. And because of the laws of karma,
what I did to plant the seed is similar
to how I see my lama acting now.
So this sweet quality that I see in my
lama nowadays--that's coming out of a
seed that I planted by behaving like him
or her in my past lives. If I experienced
my teacher as a very patient person--no
anger--then it must be that in one of my
past lives I was a person who didn't
have much anger." So we're going to go on
sort of an exploration--a detective
exploration. "That quality that I see in
my teacher"--the patience, for example--"it must
have been planted by me, myself, in a
past life." So let's go on an exploration to
our past life--just in our imagination.
And not many of us in this world have
the ability to see our past lives
directly,
but it's fun to guess, "What did I do in
the past to see this?" Then use your
imagination, have fun, enjoy! We're trying
to find powerful good seeds in our
past lives. And make a movie in your mind.
"Oh, in my past life I was
threatened by some other country's army,
but I was very patient and I refused to
fight. I refused to be angry." Then for the
movie, you're going to have to
decide what country you were in, and what
body were you in. Were you a man or were
you a woman? What race of people or culture of
people were you? Was it last year or was
it a hundred years ago, or a thousand
years ago? So make this beautiful story.
Don't be shy. And make it sweet. If
you have a teacher in this life, or you
can even imagine an
historical teacher in front of you, if
you even heard in this life the word
"Buddha," or the word "Mohammed," or the
word "Jesus," it means you're a good person
and you had some extraordinary
experiences in your past life. So we're
going to go on a pretended exploration of
our past life. Just enjoy. Make it detailed--
don't say, "Oh, I was patient."  Try
to imagine someone... specific kind of
person, "looks like this, tried to hit me, I
was patient." Okay?
Recently in my own case, if I just imagined
my past life--I cannot see it directly--I
keep getting a woman from the Middle
East. And, I don't know, maybe it was
a thousand years ago and she's a physician--
she's a doctor. Then I make a whole story
about this physician. So you'll see the
the photograph... I put it as the header
for this class. I found a picture of...
I found a picture online who looked
like her. So let's imagine. Have fun. Don't
get stuck. Don't stop--if we still have
more time, then slow down and make a nice
story. This is an exercise in the Wheel
of Life. This is an exercise in dependent
origination. The Shalistambha Sutra
said--and we're going to talk about it
next class--Buddha said, "If you see
something, then something made it happen."
So, let's have fun. We'll take about ten
minutes.
If you get tired, if you forget what
you're doing, just come back. Keep adding
more and more detail. Are you seeing your
past life directly? I think in my case,
and most of us, we are not. Are we just
imagining our past life? Yeah, we are.
But don't forget, even a movie you
imagine in your mind, those imaginations
in your mind are also coming from seeds.
You cannot imagine patience of a woman a
thousand years ago if you don't have
seeds for patience. In that sense, higher
Middle Way school, they would say this
movie we are pretending has some
reality. OK. Let's go. Let's enjoy. Choose a
beautiful quality of your teacher. Make a
beautiful story--hundred years ago, a
thousand years ago, any country you want,
any person you want to be collected the
seeds to see this lama in my life now.
Okay, let's go.
Now slowly come back.
Come back to the teacher sitting in
front of you. Look at that same good
quality, but now appreciate it differently.
"In a way, it's part of me already. I still
have that quality also--some of it."
Dedicate the good karma of this
meditation--the seventh preliminary.
Pray that all people could plant good
seeds like this one. Imagine a whole
world of people like that.
Then you can slowly open your eyes. Take a
stretch. That's dependent origination. It
will lead us into emptiness and that
emptiness will help us in the first of
the twelve steps of the wheel of dependent
origination. See you in session ten. Thank you,
Stanley!